[SPEAKER_00]: So, I heard you talking the other day about saṃsāra and it not being the round rebirth or that wheel of time image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you say that is?
[SPEAKER_00]: You mentioned it was... the translation was something like wandering on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, roaming, roaming on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saṃsārāti.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I remember correctly, this means
[SPEAKER_01]: Roaming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep roaming on and on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now here, then elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the whole idea of like a round, of rebirth, it's a notion that people develop based on this life and based on the self-centeredness of this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: By that, I mean, they use this life as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, from there, you kind of die and sort of come back in some sort of cycle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, fundamentally, if you look at the experience from the point of view of the five aggregates, there are no rounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just arising and passing away of the very same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any rebirth that you might have, it's within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then... so that's why it's not even accurate to say, ah, it's the five aggregates that get reborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that would... that would kind of imply five aggregates traveling from one birth to...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no travel from one birth to the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rebirth is within the five aggregates, as in reappearance, reemergence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within the five aggregates that you have and can know right here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why if somebody fully understands the nature of pañcakhandhā, they...
[SPEAKER_01]: They fully understood the nature of rebirth, the nature of reappearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, if somebody remembers the previous life, one previous life, or five previous lives, or five hundred eons ago, the lifetimes, all they're going to remember is the five aggregates, or one among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that saṃsāra is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your experience as a whole, it's the container of the saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, your point of view, your immediacy, the content of your senses, that can be different depending on the rebirth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be more refined, it can be... it can be coarser, it can be unpleasant, it can be torturous, but overall, in its nature, the five aggregates is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, there is no, like, coming and going and cycling around the realm of
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole world, all of the realms, all the possible realms of your rebirth are within the five aggregates which you have right here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the notion of rebirth, it's more accurately sort of reflected upon from the point of view of... like a change of rebirth would be change of immediacy, change of the degree of immediacy of your senses, the nature of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in terms of the nature of things, the nature of phenomena, nature of things to appear, there's no difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why whenever they would talk about the rebirth in the suttas, it would be like, in a sense, almost like a memory.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you remember what you've done yesterday, you remember what you've done ten days ago, you remember what you've done ten years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, some people might remember what they've done ten lifetimes ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the notion of you traveling from one river to the other, it's a notion based on the...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a projection of the external world, external point of view, independent of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a complete fallacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive things in such a purely impersonal manner, because that would require you to generally step outside of yourself, outside of the container of your five aggregates, outside of your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking something outside of your point of view, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever you can conceive, it's within your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's from your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point of view arises and ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the point... Or changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the degree of point of view can change within the container of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for example, with the animals, being the lower realm,
[SPEAKER_01]: It means their point of view, their capacities of reflection are more forcefully absorbed with the content of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why they can't step back and become aware of their situation or they can do it to a very little degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mostly, it's just absorption with immediacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hunger, hunger, fear, fear, play, play, running, chasing, fighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't just... wait a minute, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't have that much space in that reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their point of view is still absorbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why somebody can remember the previous lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's through these... through this container of the five aggregates that generates this point of view, you can actually remember more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a life doesn't last long, but a point of view can last very long.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, in a way, that's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is, again, even when people think about the notion of time, they think in this external, scientific, impersonal sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, things are in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they can say the life lasts this much, and by the point of view, lasts forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the notion, any notion of eternity, in a sense of permanence, it's wrong, because it's founded in a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the wrong view is that which contradicts the nature of the phenomena, the way they appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assuming the world outside of your five aggregates, means you're basically having a wrong assumption in regard to the nature of the way that the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could truly say that, if you want to be accurate, you can't say that five aggregates last for long, because that would imply that they are in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: While, in reality, your notion of time is already within that container of the five aggregates, your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, more accurately, you would say that five aggregates are not in time, five aggregates are off time.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, your notion of duration is already on the basis of enduring five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, not so strictly speaking, you can say, yeah, it lasts... well, it lasts infinitely, but not eternally.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's many different points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I have a point of view now, here, and your point of view... Well, again, they would assume the external point of view, they could then compare all these different points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is this point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you can know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can come close to my point of view, but you can't have my point of view, because that would require you becoming me as an individual, and that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is internal point of view, the one that you know for yourself, and then you can see other points of view, such as external points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say there are points of view, but you can't see them on the same level, or you can't even compare them on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they require you to step outside of your point of view that you're inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what about development or, well, not exactly development, but evolution, this theory of evolution?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I will continually evolve, evolve, my point of view will get better, naturally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, no, no, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: What evolves is not a point of view, it's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what can be said to evolve or proliferate, depending on how you want to call it, is the senses and the world around the immediacy, around the content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point of view is more on the level of how you regard that content, how you see it, how much you allow it to control you, to absorb you, to deprive you of your own capacity, of your own acts of reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, point of view can... it's pretty much... well, it's indirectly affected by proliferation and evolution.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, it always maintains potential of stepping back and reflecting upon the immediacy of your current birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's these realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal realm, the human realm, and they're in between that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't hear you, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the realms in between that, I think, maybe ghosts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there... there is no stepping.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no halfway realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there's no crossing between the realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you call it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The missing link.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, any notion of comparison, connection, would require an external point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Point of view that's independent of yourself, of your five aggregates, of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you know, phenomenologically speaking, is what you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in a... Based on that, you can then infer that the immediacy and the senses and the sense engagement can be different, as in
[SPEAKER_01]: It can... it can exercise a different extent, a different amount of force over you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like for animals, the senses exercise way too much force for the reflection to be able to maintain itself as much as a human can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no crossing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there is the animal realm that sits here, then there is the human realm that sits here, and then the being goes into animal realm, and then he kind of floats from animal into human or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like an externally projected notion of some sort of cosmology.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, if you're talking about it, there is no other way to talk about it than in these external terms, but those designations should not be misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it comes to your point of view, you can only see it from the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how... that's how... that's how the Buddha would refer that, like, an arahant or somebody who is fully understood, understood the saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by traveling in previous lives or waiting for the future lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he understood the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understood the... sorry, not the content, the container, the basis on account of any different content can manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by saying different content means different birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Content of an animal realm or content of a deva realm, as in the refinement of the content, the type of engagement of the content, that's basically what you can
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't necessarily develop each birth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not getting better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're getting worse, better, worse, better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, based on your actions, they will kind of play the part into what kind of content you're going to be... your point of view will be paired with later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, again, you can... you don't have to think about previous life and future life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the principle that you can extend.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can think within this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the actions you're making now are quite unwholesome, harming a lot of people, for example, causing lots of damage,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can safely assume that your whole life is heading in that direction, so then in five, six years, when the whole world is against you, they're trying to imprison you, they chase you because of the crimes you committed, your content has been significantly changed to... to like... like more pressing, more enduring, more unpleasant, because of your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been affecting you in that manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: If... if... if your actions are in this very life, are actually not harming anybody,
[SPEAKER_01]: are helpful to everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, that's going to be influencing your environment the most.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not 100%, because there are many other factors that can play the part, but to a great deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a person doesn't go around committing crimes, they don't have to worry about whether anybody's going to get them, catch them, exercise revenge on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those who do, that becomes your daily environment, that becomes your daily content of the phenomena that keeps appearing from your point of view, of the further actions you do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could then see, if you carry on that kind of behavior for years, it's not a big stretch to assume that, oh yeah, so, when this life sort of breaks apart, when this body breaks apart,
[SPEAKER_01]: The content that's going to re-arise, it's just going to carry on further in the same direction, because that's how you've been exercising your point of view and your actions and your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no, like, a natural end to saṃsāra, where you just get better, better, better, evolve in a good way, evolve, evolve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in a way, it's, again, it's not like that you re-enter saṃsāra, you are the saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: The five aggregates affected by ignorance is what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: This, this experience of the five aggregates, for somebody who is not enlightened, that's, that's already what saṃsāra is, which means this experience is just gonna stay infinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless a person frees this very experience from that ignorance, then it will not reappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: The content will not... well, you won't be paired with any content, with any form.
[SPEAKER_01]: That point of view will not be paired.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will just go extinct, as the Buddha would describe nibbāna as extinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't go anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It... well, it doesn't go anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would require you to jump from a point A in space to a point B in space, which then assumes the external point of view of space, which is only... can be based on the five aggregates right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why your experience is not in space and in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's off space and off time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get the notion of space based on your perceptions and notion of time pretty much based on your feelings and their endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop thinking in terms of I'm in space and time, then the whole notion of rebirth becomes much more intelligible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it just fits perfectly with pretty much everything else that you can know right here and right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Point of view is beyond time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's off time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not beyond time, because again, that assumes time, and now it's something beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Notion of time, it's basically a result of the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Notion of time and space is a result of point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a result of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, like, again, you can think of it on the level of this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, you have... you... today is, you know, a new day.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do... you do certain... you do certain things and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you wake up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, again, it's a new day.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, you have a memory of yesterday and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will affect your choices today.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have assumption of tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to affect your choice today and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's all within your experience as a whole, within your point of view, within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be asking yourself, oh, was it me from yesterday, the same who became the one today, and is going to be the one tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just me who went to sleep yesterday, and now I woke up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in a way, it's a new day from a reference point of view, of yesterday, as in from a memory.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is within this experience today.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can extend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yesterday, ten years ago, ten lifetimes ago, you've just been waking up in different environments, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why... oh, what does... what... the question of who gets reborn is a wrong question, because it assumes this external floating from one life to another, and what is it that it changes and goes there?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha wouldn't even answer it, because it's based on a completely wrong premise of this external world point of view, that it's kind of independent of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't possibly conceive anything like that, because if something... if you're conceiving something independent of you, you can only do so on account of depending it upon your experience of the five aggregates, which means it's not truly independent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's a completely wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, any question that will come out of it, as in, who gets reborn from life number one to a life number two,
[SPEAKER_01]: It just requires this non-existent external world, independent of your experience, independent of your sense of being and your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, yeah, just ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yourself, that you can remember from ten years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who's that?
[SPEAKER_01]: How did that person from ten years ago become you today?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that's... well, that's not really a right question to formulate like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did it... because you would assume that something has kind of traveled independent of you, from a point of view in the past, to a point of view right here.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, it's just... no, it's just... this point of... this experience has been enduring for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: There have been changes on a particular level, while overall it was remaining the same container.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same nature of perception... You've been having different perceptions, different intentions, you've been performing different actions ten years ago, because you had different values and different views, but overall, it was still the nature of perception, the nature of feeling, the nature of intention, the nature of the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, you can't step outside of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant doesn't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He actually realizes that
[SPEAKER_01]: Outside is inconceivable, so he stops conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doing so, he removes ignorance in regard to the inside of himself, in regard to the nature of perception, feeling, intention, the nature of the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how he extinguishes that container.
[SPEAKER_01]: It ceases to be the fertile ground for this maintenance of the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't assume outside of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's... Well, even Sotāpanna stops assuming that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the fundamental, the core of the external assumption of your own experience is attavāda, the external sense of self, pretty much, independent of this experience and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they would ask, who gets reborn?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they assume the impersonal world, the impersonal space and time from which things just flow, from one birth to the other realm, to this realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no matter the realm, the nature of the five aggregates is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, oh, so if you want to find
[SPEAKER_01]: How it is in more subtle realms or coarser realms, you can do so on account of understanding the nature of this experience that you have, because it's within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what... and that's why it's called roaming onwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just this experience just keeps perpetuating itself on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha, again, he did give a simile that illustrates that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, it's like a man leaving his home village and then goes to the next village.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, from that village, he goes to the next village.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, at 20th village, they ask him, where did you come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, well, before this village, I was in this village.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before that, I was in another village, and another village, and another village.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, if you were to describe it to somebody else, it would sound like that external manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: But from his point of view, he was always in the village that he was in.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't step outside of himself and then explain to himself how he didn't need to, how he from one village crossed to another village.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it was just, I was in this village, then I went on to another village.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each time he was in different village, he had a different content of a village.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of the nature of his experience, perception of the village, intentions of the village, feelings in the village were the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature remained the same, the nature of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, even if you remember 500 lifetimes more from before, all you're remembering is these five aggregates right here, right now, or one among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said, you cannot... you cannot know the five aggregates directly, or you cannot... you assume them... Well, you cannot examine them and take them apart again, because that would require the external point of view in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only see the insides.
[SPEAKER_01]: of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you think, oh, this is the inside, you already start implying the assumption, the conceiving of the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives in matter, from matter, apart from matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives matter is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives... and then he goes on in that Mūla Pāryāya Sutta for all the other aggregates and all the other ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: By implicitly perceiving it as, ah, this is the inside, you automatically assume the outside, to an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to undo that implicit conceiving and then the assumption of the outside will fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Undo the implicit conceiving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you, again, you undo that implicit conceiving not on account of finding out the external view of the five aggregates and then examining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: One by one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You undo it by stop regarding it as mine, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing that it's independent of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing that it's subjected to destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were truly able to access it and control it, it would obey you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would listen you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would go with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, like some people, some minds can go to the subtle level of being mindful of the earth element.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, whether you're mindful of the earth element, whether you're mindful of the body seated on this chair, it's, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can arrive at the same goal, without needing to refine it to the point of the earth element.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being mindful of your experience as a whole, bound up with this body, with this form, without overdoing your thought into assuming the external world point of view, but without becoming negligent in regard to your own absorption with your own senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, if a person wants to reflect along these lines, they can within this... with experience and the memories of this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I ask you, where were you, I don't know, five days ago, you say, I was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where were you ten years ago?
[SPEAKER_01]: I was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, yeah, there was some change, but within your point of view hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your views might have changed, but the direction of you having views, the experience as a whole, the nature of perception, the nature of body,
[SPEAKER_01]: The form, the nature of feeling, the nature of perception, the nature of intention, the nature of consciousness, that hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That container has remained unchanged since you can remember.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remember since when you were two years old.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of where it stopped.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it only stops because your memory stops there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the principle carries on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means then, yes, some people can then start remembering more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still within the same principle of the memory that you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, it's not correct to say that it's, oh, yeah, it's my sense of self that got reborn, or it was previously in this life, now it's in this life, then it will go in another life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in space and time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's memory?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where does memory sit?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does memory sit?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it sits in that infinity of change on a more particular level, within the container that stays the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The container of your experience as a whole, the container of the five aggregates, the container of your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why memory is, in a way, endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there was no first beginning, before which it didn't exist, and then you became.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, Avijja has no first point, when it manifests.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't be there, but it is there, and its being there is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why once you undo it, cannot re-arise, cannot reappear, cannot re-emerge, because it was never meant to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ignorance, the assumption of the external point of view, all of that, was not meant to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't fit there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The upādāna is not the five aggregates, cannot be the five aggregates, cannot become the five aggregates, cannot enter the five aggregates, but cannot be found apart from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, desire and lust, which is another way of saying, misconceiving the five aggregates, the upādāna, the assumptions are there in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop misconceiving it, the upādāna fades.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so does the one doing none.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more being bound with the content like this, then like that, then another one, then another one.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what generates saṃsāra is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: What generates?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not the right word.
[SPEAKER_00]: What keeps it going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What maintains saṃsāra?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't have that...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have ignorance, saṃsāra cannot be maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just back to the memory, you're saying, where does it sit?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mental... Again, where does it sit implies placement in space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's over here.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that assumes the external point of view, where you can place it, like a box on a shelf or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: In space.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: At most, that can just be a figure of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if that figure of speech is taken literally, as in, then you start assuming that it's in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in the brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's in the brain, it's in a center or in some molecules there or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's no more in your brain that it's more in your toes.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, consciousness is not in your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's paired with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, any notions that you have on account... any notions that you have of your body, it's on the basis of conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any notions that you have on account of... any notions that you have in regard to consciousness, it's on the basis of the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Conscious body is the basis that you cannot step outside of, nor separate and investigate separately.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why whenever you look at the body, you're conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you're trying to discern consciousness, the necessary living body needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is when people look at either body of consciousness and then develop the view that places them underneath or rather as more fundamental than the dyad of conscious body that you have right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you have to realize that no... no... doesn't matter how pleasing the notions of the body you might develop,
[SPEAKER_01]: And the theories and the views, that can only be done within the container of conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why scientific view, it's inherently wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not wrong in terms of the content, but wrong in terms of the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you cannot use science to arrive and explain the nature of being, the nature of experience, the nature of feelings, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why whenever the scientists try to talk about feelings and describe feelings, they end up just describing
[SPEAKER_01]: perceptions of sensations in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But perception is perception and feeling is feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't feel your perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, perceptions and feelings in the same sense like body and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're paired, but they're independent of each other, but they're inseparable from each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: He said perception, feeling and intentions are conjoined.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot take them apart and examine them
[SPEAKER_01]: Separate from the other two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that's the basis that you cannot conceive different in any other shape or form.
[SPEAKER_01]: And any conceivings you have, it's within that container of that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, if your conceivings are contradicting the basis, it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why if you were to have a scientific view in terms of practicing the dhamma, it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it contradicts the nature of the basis on account of which you developed the scientific view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That external world that you cannot actually conceive truly, you cannot access in that impersonal manner as the science leads you to believe.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always have a point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the notion of, no, this is beyond the point of view, is within your point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, this is external to my point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can only see that through your point of view, which means it's not external.
[SPEAKER_01]: The true external... Well, see, you can't even designate it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you say the true external, well, it's not external then, because you're talking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're designating something, and if there is something, even an ambiguous notion of external world, it's within this container of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's not truly external.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there is no real matter, a real reality behind these appearances, or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What appears, that's what's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, like I should speak about God, like a God is like this... Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're conceiving it through, through labeling it, through designating how it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot express the deity, the eternal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just expressed it, by saying it's, it's not expressible.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter what you express, it is within.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, yep, yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's, you realize, you can't step outside of your, of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was never the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you stop looking for some hidden transcendental realities, which is what usually think... what usually people think Arahantship is.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you realize, you can't... you... all you have to do is stop conceiving that there is outside to be found.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because conceiving the outside is conceiving the independence of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a definition of atavāda, an independent sense of self, independent of the five aggregates, independent of the form, feeling, perceptions, intentions and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, any notion of that independence is based on this form, feeling, perception, intentions, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's actually secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it cannot be independent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all a person needs to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop assuming the external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop assuming that master self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop conceiving it as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's Mūla Parīyā's sutta in a nutshell.
[SPEAKER_00]: The very first sutta in Lajjanaikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that before anything there was nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's something, because you're thinking of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if something is truly nothing, then you can't even designate it as nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As absence of something, it's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you can't even think it, and let alone designate it as something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you keep trying to think it, means you just keep trying to contradict yourself, your own experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you shouldn't think it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you should realize that it's unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the projection towards thinking it, you realize, well, that's already thinkable within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it cannot stand for that which is truly unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the thought of unthinkable stops conceiving something that it's thinkable, that's when the thought recognizes its own extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some philosophers speak about being and nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes, but the ones that do, ended up assuming the external world from which they very plausibly defined being and nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's already then contradicting the basic phenomenological principle that they used to arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that sutta, Madhyamikāya 1, it says, a person can experience nibbāna, but he assumes nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can have the experience of absence, of greed, aversion, delusion, but he can have it affected by the assumption of external sense of self, external master, external point of view, that there's external scientific order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_01]: That experience of not-self, that experience of freedom from greed, aversion, delusion, is appropriated by that fully gratuitous view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, he conceives that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives apart from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, he cannot steady his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because of that, that nibbāna cannot become the experience that he develops fully, consistently.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is the nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is another sutta in Majjhima Nikāra, later on, when the Buddha gives a similar description how a person with his conceit thinks, oh, this is nibbāna, I'm attaining nibbāna, this nibbāna is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, yeah, what he refers to is the actual nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because of the self-centered point of view, because of those assumptions of self and mastery, he does not enter that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He cannot sustain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a different nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a cop-out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like when people try, oh, no, it's a different nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an easy way to dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha himself said, although he asserts that which is nibbāna, he doesn't enter it because he can't study his experience in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He keeps misconsuming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of death being the end, the ending of things, from what you were saying,
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't seem to be the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death, it's the end of the assumptions that you developed based on the familiarity with the current content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, it's the end of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's far from the end of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: The true end of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's far from the end of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, most people, the entire life, the sense of self, the views, are based on the content of this present experience, on that assumption of the external world and that whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, death ends all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to... Yeah, if you stop...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you removed all the conceivings and stopped wrongly assuming things in regard to this content of this experience, this life,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no death, hence the deathless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is death can apply only where the content, where the assumptions in regard to the content of your senses exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the assumptions, that is the true deathless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the notion of death is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's almost what a lot of people think that death is, you know, the complete, some ending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again... See, the fact that you can think, that you can have a notion of complete nothingness, well, that's something.
[SPEAKER_01]: That notion is real as such, which means it's not the true nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's a true nothingness, you couldn't think it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the non-conceiving death... Non-conceiving death means stop assuming wrong things in regard to the nature of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what non-conceiving death means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have an understanding of what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what development is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing the assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you see nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can step into it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see it, externally examine it, because if you are seeing it like that, you're misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can enter nibbāna by removing all the assumptions that misconceive what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, your experience automatically becomes experience of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like you do the work of removing the assumptions, and then the gates open, and then you walk into the nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing the work, removing all the conceiving, is what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it missed again?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, you are striving to bring about the ending being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not striving to find, as I said, some kind of external transcendental entity that you merge with or receives you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're striving to stop misconceiving this very experience, to stop appropriating it as mine, stop entertaining mistaken gratuitous assumption in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will undo the being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what being is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mistake in regard to things that appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mistake of ownership, mistake of the sense of self, mistake of permanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people say that it sounds like a kind of trying to kill yourself, you know, like a suicide, an ultimate suicide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the suicide of ignorance, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the suicide of the self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not the suicide of the content on account of which you develop the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like people killing the five aggregates... trying to kill the five aggregates because they can't get rid of upādāna in regard to the pañcakhandha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not knowing where the problem is, you're attacking it at a wrong... at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's usually what suicide is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attacking the body, trying to kill the body, so it will kind of kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have undone your sense of self, then you don't care about living or killing the body, because it's not suicide then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's suicide when you're trying to get rid of that self, sense of self, by destroying the environment that supports it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at it as the way I described it, you can't destroy the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just keep changing the content of it through getting a different birth, different rebirth, which means you then can't... you don't... you don't do anything about the underlying problem of misconceiving the content that resulted in you having the self-view in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might have annihilated the temporary or rather the particular content, but overall, your mistake in regard to the nature of the content stays the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you keep getting born
[SPEAKER_01]: On and on and on again, and keep reappropriating things, misappropriating, misconceiving, and keep being bound by saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the true suicide, the one that can truly kill that sense of self, is the one that doesn't kill the body, doesn't aim at the body, but actually undoes, undoes the ignorance in regard to the body, in regard to the phenomenon of the body,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when nibbāna is annihilation of greed, aversion, delusion, of conceivings, of appropriation of the sense of self, but not annihilation of the content and of the environment and of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's obviously suicide seems to be quite a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, because it's, you see, it's just a further proliferation of already, of the original mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: You misconceive the content of your experience, you're not seeing the nature of it, you develop the sense of ownership and sense of self, the external self that's in charge of this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, despite being paired with unpleasant feelings and so on, you still can't see that you are not in control of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And instead of taking that as a way of liberating yourself from that gratuitous assumption of ownership, of control, you then try to, like, destroy the whole thing, while actually aiming at destroying that ownership and that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said before, as the suttas say, the upādāna, the assumption of self or any other assumption, it's not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not to be found apart from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to discern the nature of the five aggregates, so you stop having desire and lust in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, the sense of self that's being simultaneously generated by it ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people don't know that, so then they just try to destroy the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just dismiss the problem, and that's how you solve the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why suicide is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, on account of the problem, you just perpetuated the problem, but then remove the possibility of understanding the problem,
[SPEAKER_01]: In any foreseeable future.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what about people who have understood the problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: The arahants?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, their suicide, like in the suttas, when arahants committed, it's not a suicide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were not aiming or trying to get rid of that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not, obviously, not distraught or anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they, as the Buddha would say, he wouldn't use the word death as like they kill themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would say they would... the ones they were sick, physically sick, the body was just in this horrible falling apart state, dysentery and what not, beyond repair, beyond medicine, and they already uprooted everything in regard to that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then they just, literally, sped up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quicken the process.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quicken the... that which was already coming to its end.
[SPEAKER_01]: By freeing the sense of... freeing the assumption of the external world, freeing the... removing the notion of appropriation, the body that has still remained for an arahant, the five aggregates, are the last.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no desire and lust in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no reappearance of the content anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once this body breaks apart, it will not carry on, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the true ending.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for an arahant, like Venerable Chana in Madhyamani Kaya,
[SPEAKER_01]: ...who was so ill and so sick in constant discomfort, he thought, well, he has no reason to wait whether this body will break apart in five years or five days, because he'd done the work of uprooting everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing more to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing more to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, because the circumstances of that body were so disagreeable, he had no reason to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would he endure it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to prove, nothing to do anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, he's just decided to kill that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, just to, instead of waiting for five years for it to disintegrate, he'd done it in five days.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a valid thing to do only after you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, if there is still desire and lust in regard to that dead body that you're trying to kill, means you are committing a suicide.
[SPEAKER_01]: To a various degree, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending on how much desire and lust is a motivator for that action.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for an arahant, it can't be any.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for him, it's truly just... just... just... just... fast... like speeding up the process of the disintegration of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there is desire and lust in regards to it, they are not disintegrating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you do remain bound with the nature of them, which means you will keep reappearing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reason why suicide is very unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because by doing it, you end up binding yourself most likely with even less fortunate content of your five aggregates, which will then prevent the possibility of reflection necessary for removing the assumption and developing wisdom and understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, the animal realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through your own ignorance, greed, aversion, delusion and assumptions, wrong assumptions in the sense of self, you committed acts then, that removed even further the possibility for you understanding that problem in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And which means then you have to keep enduring saṃsāra much longer, because of your own ignorant actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why somebody who is not an arahant, it's actually better not to
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, a lot of people who are not even practicing, they've got a heavy disease, painful disease, some cancer of some kind, and there is no cure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, they're in a lot of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they choose, say, euthanasia.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: To kill themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no hope.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's true that the time will come when there is no hope.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is not true is that that pain is the greatest pain that you can experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is still affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the worst pain of the human realm might not be anything in comparison to the pains of being paired with lower types of content in your future reappearances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of... again, any reference you can make, it's based on this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it seems unbearable, but you have actually no idea which... where you are heading.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's better to try and make absolutely most of it while you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will die eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Try to endure pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to endure it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the developed mind can endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind did not have
[SPEAKER_01]: Or if it has been undermined and eroded for a longer time, so it couldn't develop to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, there is a serious amount of responsibility, eh... if a person commits suicide and they still have the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're still a kutujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: They still haven't understood even what nature and nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... because they might be, eh... removing that possibility of understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They remove it for a long, long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the... if the next... next births and rebirths and reappearances, whatever you want to call it, are lower than the human realm, or even if they are higher, if it's just infused with divine pleasures, you won't be thinking and reflecting much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you really want to make the most of this... this opportunity that you have, where you can reflect with that right balance, which is what human realm is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you've done that work,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you fully free the whole experience of the five areas, there's no external assumptions, no conceivings, there is no suicide, there is no murder, there is no death.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is something that everyone should be training towards, because everyone is going some some way or... Yeah, ultimately, that should be... that's pretty much the soul... the aim of any being in any realm should be freeing themselves from being bound with that... with the content of their experience, with the saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just in terms of enduring pain, painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's like the beginning of restraint as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're healthy, you start practicing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when the senses start falling apart, if you haven't practiced restraint and enduring, you won't be able to...